Guide to the Daniel Rubin Papers TAM.657
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Daniel Rubin Papers
1930s-2015
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rubin, Daniel, 1931-2015
Rubin, Dorothy
TAM.657
122 Linear Feet in 228 manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, 13 record cartons, and 6 cassette boxes
224 audiocassettes
2.54 Gigabytes in 1030 computer files
1 CD
Mortimer Daniel Rubin (1931-2015) was a prominent member of the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA). He held many leadership positions in the Communist Party including National Youth Secretary, National Organizational Secretary, Head of the Department of Economic and Social Rights, and Education Secretary. His papers provide a broad view of Rubin's political life and his work within the Communist Party, documenting how his personal and intellectual life were heavily intertwined with his political activism. They consist of national Communist Party administrative files documenting his leadership position within the Party, including correspondence, meeting minutes, memoranda, bulletins, notes, drafts of essays and official Party statements, educational course outlines, and collected articles and pamphlets. The collection also contains files related to Rubin's split from the CPUSA in 1991 and his involvement in the creation of the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism. Other files document Rubin's work after he renewed his Communist Party membership in 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions with the exception of box 241, folders 1-3, and box 242, folders 2-8. Access to these folders are restricted until 2068.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Daniel Rubin in 2014; additional materials were purchased from Dorothoy Rubin in 2016. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2014.168 and 2015.010.
Appraisal
Approximately 12 boxes of newspaper clippings files, periodicals, and collected articles were removed from the collection. Clippings were largely from trade publications and held little research value, while publications included copies of Communist Party produced periodicals and publications from related organizations that are already included in the Tamiment Library's serials collections. An additional 14 boxes of books and pamphlets that duplicated materials already in Tamiment's holding were also deaccessioned.
A small amount of financial records and receipts were also removed from the collection. These items contained personal financial information and contained limited research value.
Additionally, several boxes containing printed out emails and online articles related to local New York City politics from the early 2000s were weeded by the archivist and bulk emails from political campaigns and progressive listservs were deaccessioned. Only the emails that documented Rubin's direct involvement with these campaigns were retained. These included emails directly addressed to Rubin, or discussion list conversations in which Rubin participated.
Other materials removed from the collection include duplicate buttons, lapel pins, duplicates audio tapes of the Gus Hall program Update, and an off-air recording of an episode of NPR's All Things Considered.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into five series, which reflect Daniel Rubin's work and leadership roles within the Communist Party of the United States. Materials in Series I-IV are arranged by Communist Party departments: Series I: National Organizational Department, Series II: Youth Commission, Series III: Economic and Social Rights Commission, and Series IV: Education Department, which Rubin led at different times during his membership. Inclusion of materials in these series, however, is not exclusively limited to the years he directed these departments as he contributed to efforts of various departments even when he was not in a leadership position. Series I: National Organizational Department has been further divided into subseries to reflect major functions of the national Party work: Subseries I.A: General Files, Subseries I.B: Clubs and Districts, Subseries I.C: Conventions, Subseries I.D: Elections, and Subseries I.E: National Council and National Committee Meetings. Series V: Post 1991 Spilt, documents Rubin's political work in the years following the major rupture in the Communist Party at the 1991 National Convention.
Biographical Note
Mortimer Daniel Rubin (1931-2015) was a prominent member of the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA). Rubin was born in Philadelphia, PA in 1931. Better known as Daniel Rubin, he was raised in a Jewish, communist household and involved in progressive and communist activism from an early age. In 1947 he joined the Progressive Citizens of America and was founding member of the Young Progressives of America. He attended Swarthmore College where he joined Citizens for a Free City College, as well as American Youth for Democracy, a Communist Party affiliated youth organization. He began law school at University of Pennsylvania in 1953 and in that year became one of three members in the Eastern-Pennsylvania Labor Youth League. Rubin attended his first CPUSA convention in 1956 as a delegate to the 16th National Convention. In that year, he became a board member of the CPUSA's Philadelphia district and the district's Youth Secretary. In 1959 Rubin was elected to the National Committee of the CPUSA and invited to move to New York to become the organization's National Youth Secretary, a position he held until 1964. Rubin became the Party's National Organizational Secretary in 1964, a position he held until 1974. Rubin was deeply involved in CPUSA national work until 1991, serving as head of the Department of Economic and Social Rights from 1974 to 1980, and Educational Director from 1981 to 1992. Following the 1991 National Convention, Rubin and several other prominent members split from the Party and formed the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism. Rubin renewed his membership with CPUSA in 2000 and remained an active member until his death in 2015. During these years his work focused primarily on club and district organizing in Brooklyn and New York State.
Related Materials
This collection contains materials that are closely related to the Communist Party of the United States of America Records (TAM 132). The Daniel Rubin Papers contain organizational files of the Communist Party USA, which he retained as a result of his management of various Party departments.
Many audio tapes in this collection are duplicated in the CPUSA Records (TAM 132), which contain more complete holdings of Communist Party events and meetings recordings.
Scope and Contents
The Daniel Rubin Papers (dated 1940s-2015) provide a broad view of Daniel Rubin's political life and his work within the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA). Daniel Rubin's papers document how his personal and intellectual life were heavily intertwined with his political activism, and in particular his work for the Party. Most well represented among his papers are files from Rubin's work as National Organizational Secretary and his work with national organizational bodies of the Party such as the National Committee and the National Board. Also well represented in his papers are correspondence, reports, and organizing files related to his leadership of the Youth Commission, the Economic and Social Rights Commission, and the Education Department. The collection also contains files related to Rubin's split from the CPUSA in 1991 and his involvement in the creation of the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism. Other files document Rubin's work after he renewed his Communist Party membership in 2000. During that time, Rubin worked to strengthen the CPUSA's Brooklyn Club and served as a member of the New York District Executive Committee and the CPUSA National Committee. These materials consist of National Party correspondence, minutes, memoranda, bulletins, notes, drafts of essays and official Party statements, educational course outlines, and collected articles and pamphlets. Rubin was deeply also interested in the history of Judaism and communism, and his papers dated after 1991 include extensive research files on international Jewish issues and the role of Jews in Communist Party.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Communism -- United States -- 20th century; Communism -- New York (State) -- New York; Marxism -- United States.; Communism and education.; Youth movements -- United States.; Jews -- Political activity -- United States.; Elections -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Rubin, Dorothy; Communist Party of the United States of America; Committees of Correspondence (U.S.); Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism; Labor Youth League; Young Communist League of the U.S.; Young Workers Liberation League
- Series I: Communist Party National Organizational Bureau and Department, 1930-1991; 47 Linear Feet in 74 manuscript boxes, 9 record cartons, 1 half manuscript box and 6 cassette boxes; 145 audiocassettes
  Scope and Contents
  This series comprises the bulk of the collection, and documents Rubin's activities as the National Party Secretary. It includes materials related to Rubin's work organizing National Party Conventions, meetings, and general Party correspondence. Included among these materials is Rubin's research and writings for CPUSA pamphlets, periodicals, and reports to which he contributed. Other materials in this series include collected buttons and audio recordings documenting CPUSA lectures, programs, and political campaigns. Materials in this series also document the National Organizational Department's work with club and districts. They include correspondence and memoranda between local clubs and the national office, as well as flyers, agenda, notes, and drafts related to recruitment, planning for courses and seminars, and local meetings.
  Arrangement
  This series is divided in to five subseries based on major functions of national Party work. Materials are arranged alphabetically within subseries.
  - Subseries I.A: General Files, 1930-1991; 26 Linear Feet in 28 manuscript boxes, 4 record cartons, 1 half manuscript box, and 6 cassette boxes; 108 audiocassettes
    Files in this subseries are arranged alphabetically by topic. Organization Bureau and Organization Department files are maintained in general groupings, which are listed in roughly chronological order. This reflects the order in which Rubin maintained his files, and the loose categorization he used in arranging his files.
    This subseries consists of general files created as a result of Daniel Rubin's national work for the Communist Party. It includes correspondence, meeting minutes, research files, draft reports, and select administrative files documenting Rubin's work as National Organizational Secretary and his work for national Party departments. Files of particular interest in this subseries include National Organizational Secretary correspondence, Organization Bureau meeting minutes, and Organization Department general files. The Organization Bureau and Organization Department refer to the same department in the Communist Party, and were used interchangeably by Rubin. These files contain Rubin's notes from national department meetings and correspondence between Rubin and Party leaders, the bulk of which are dated between 1970 and 1990.
    Collected memorabilia related to Rubin's work in the Communist Party is also included in this subseries. These items include a large collection of political buttons and lapel pins dated from the 1930s to the early 2000s. They touch on a wide array of topics including elections, anti-war and anti-nuclear protests, labor movements, and socialism. Lapel pins feature images of Vladimir Lenin and Karl Marx as well as the insignia of various Communist organizations.
    This subseries also contains a significant amount of recordings on audio cassette tapes. Tapes feature lectures, workshops, reports, and conference discussions on topics related to economics, politics, and Party ideology. Speakers featured in these recording include Herbert Aptheker, Arnold Becchetti, Alva Buxenbaum, Gil Green, Gus Hall, Esther Rand, Daniel Rubin, and Henry Winston. Titles for recordings were derived from annotations on the cassettes, and some topics and speakers featured on these recordings are unidentified.
    - African-American Equality, undated (Box 234, Cassette 36-37)
    - Afro-American Liberation Seminar Opening Remarks: Henry Winston, 1981 January 17-18 (Box 235, Cassette 77)
    - Anti-Monopoly Strategy, undated (Box 233, Cassette 1-2)
    - Aptheker Dinner Forms, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Aptheker, Herbert: Anti-Sovietism and US National Interests, 1981 January (Box 238, Cassette 183)
    - Aptheker Testimonial Dinner Sponsor Lists and Other Miscellaneous Materials, 1966; 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Articles By and About Danny Rubin, 1989-2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Asian-American Liberation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Biographies of Du Bois, John Brown, Debs, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Biographies of Dennis Eugene, Ben Davis, Foster, Flynn, Ford, 1962; undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Biographies of John Reed, Jim Dolsen, etc., 1952; 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Biographies of Henry Winston, etc., 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bird, Acie, undated (Box 237, Cassette 173-174)
    - Black and White Getting It Together (B & W G.I.T.), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11, Box 234, Cassette 224)
    - Budget, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Budget: Regan Administration, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Buxenbaum, Alva: on Women, 1985 April 10 (Box 237, Cassette 164)
    - Browder, Earl: Remarks at National Convention, Communist Political Association, 1945 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Adams, David, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Books and Reviews, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Buxenbaum Divorce, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - CAND N. TE, undated (Box 237, Cassette 171-172)
    - Communist Party: Constitutions, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 3-6)
    - Coal Commission, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Cohen, Muriel and Patrick Suzeau, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Commentaries on CPUSA, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Communist Party: Dialog, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - Communist Party: Dialog Acknowledgement Letter, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Communist Party: Dialog Articles, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Communist Party: Dialog Finances, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Communist Party: Dialog General, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
    - Communist Party: Dialog Not Used, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    - Communist Party: Dialog, Pre-Convention, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Communist Party: Dialog Report, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Communist Party: Dialog Questionnaire, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Communist Party: General Correspondence, 1976-1987 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
    - Communist Party Memos: All Departments, 1970-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5-11)
    - Communist Party Memos: All Departments, 1970-1989 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Correspondence: Danny's Miscellaneous, 1990-1992 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    - Correspondence: On Possible Publications, 1971-1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Culture, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 6-8)
    - Czechoslovakia, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
    - Czechoslovakia Events, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Day Care and Summer Camps, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Daily World, 1968 (Box 219, Folder 1-2)
    - Daily World: Campaign, 1968 (Box 219, Folder 3-4)
    - Daily World: Circulation, 1967-1970 (Box 219, Folder 5-6)
    - Daily World: Circulation Drive, 1970 (Box 219, Folder 7)
    - Daily World: Management, 1970-1973 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Daily World: Management, 1970-1973 (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
    - Daily World: Press Articles, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Daily World: The Worker, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Defense, 1967-1970 (Box 219, Folder 8-10)
    - Defense, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
    - Democratic Socialist, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Democratic Socialist (DSA) and New American Movement (NAM), 1980-1982 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Democratic Centralism, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 6-8)
    - Democratic Centralism, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Democratic Centralism: Documents, 1946; 1990s (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Dennis, Peggy: Manuscript, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Discussion on Japan-US Relations, 1988 June 18 (Box 236, Cassette 74, 208)
    - East Side: Danny Rubin, 1977 February 12 (Box 238, Cassette 182)
    - Economics, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 4-8)
    - Economics: Not Really Marxist, undated (Box 233, Cassette 3)
    - Economic Commission, 1986-1991 (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
    - Examining the Crisis in Steel, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Factionalism, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Farm, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Finances, 1969 (Box 219, Folder 11)
    - Finances, 1976-1989 (Box 10, Folder 4-7)
    - Finances: Dues and Contribution Ledger, 1962 (Box 219, Folder 12)
    - Finances: Advance Tax Assessment, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Finances: Budget Cutting, 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Finances: Budgets, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Finances: Building, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Finances: Tax Exempt, 1988-1989 (Box 10, Folder 12-14)
    - Forms, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Finances and Wages, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Fundraising, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - General Peace Literature, 1967-1968 (Box 219, Folder 14)
    - Green, Gil: DSOC Report, 1981 August 11 (Box 237, Cassette 181)
    - Greek Work, 1970-1972 (Box 219, Folder 15)
    - Hall, Gus: #83, Perlo, 1988 (Box 236, Cassette 123)
    - Hall, Gus: Economy, 1973 September (Box 237, Cassette 142)
    - Hall, Gus: Report to Central Committee, 1983 January 29 (Box 236, Cassette 126-127)
    - Hall, Gus: Speech at Milwaukee Rally with Introduction by Henry Winston, 1982 April 24 (Box 236, Cassette 128)
    - Hall, Gus: Draft Report, undated (Box 233, Cassette 4, Box Shared Tamiment 111, Cd ref13)
    - Hall, Gus: Update, 1989 September 5 (Box 233, Cassette 5, Box Shared Tamiment 111, Cd ref10)
    - Hall, Gus: Update, 1991 March 20 (Box 233, Cassette 6)
    - Hall, Gus: Update, 1991 April 2 (Box 233, Cassette 7, Box Shared Tamiment 111, Cd ref11)
    - Hall, Gus: Update, 1991 April 16 (Box 233, Cassette 8, Box Shared Tamiment 111, Cd ref8)
    - Hall, Gus: WPEN Forum, 1964 (Box 236, Cassette 124-125)
    - Halls for Meeting Carnegie, etc., undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Hamerquist Manuscript, undated (Box 219, Folder 16)
    - Healey, Dorothy: Documents, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 5-11)
    - Healey, Dorothy, Peggy Dennis, Al Richmond, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
    - Health, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - History: Jesse Lemisch, 1969 (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
    - History of American Communist Colonies, 1964; 1973 (Box 12, Folder 7-8)
    - History Commission, 1987-1990 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - History of the Communist Party, 1937-1972 (Box 219, Folder 17)
    - Housing: Miscellaneous, 1966 (Box 219, Folder 18)
    - Ideological Discussion: Winston, 1986 January 7 (Box 237, Cassette 151)
    - Ideological Discussion: Charlene Mitchell: Peace, 1986 May 30 (Box 237, Cassette 152)
    - Ideological Discussion: Lou Diskin, 1989 June (Box 237, Cassette 153)
    - Ideological Discussion: Bob Lindsay, 1989 May 16 (Box 237, Cassette 154)
    - Ideological Discussion: Jim West, 1989 May 23 (Box 237, Cassette 155)
    - Ideological Discussion: John Bactell, 1989 May 23 (Box 237, Cassette 156)
    - Ideological Discussion: Lee Dlugin, 1989 May 6 (Box 237, Cassette 157)
    - Ideological Discussion: Arnold Becchetti #53, 1989 July 5 (Box 237, Cassette 158)
    - Ideological Discussion: Arnold Becchetti #56, 1989 July 5 (Box 237, Cassette 159)
    - Imperialism, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Imported Publications, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Industrial Concentration Conference, 1968-1969 (Box 219, Folder 19)
    - International Commission, 1990-1991 (Box 13, Folder 5-7)
    - International Economic Crisis, 1999 March 21 (Box 236, Cassette 105-106)
    - International Economy 1, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - International Parties, 1968-1972 (Box 14, Folder 1-7)
    - International Publishers: Ephemera, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - International Publishers, 1971-1972 (Box 219, Folder 20)
    - International Publishers, 1971-1972 (Box 220, Folder 1)
    - International Publishers, 1984-1988 (Box 15, Folder 1-5)
    - Indian Liberation, 1969-1972 (Box 220, Folder 2)
    - Iran Gate, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Irish Songs: The Clancy Bros. and Tommy Makem; Songs of Tommy Makem, undated (Box 237, Cassette 145)
    - Irish Songs: The Irish Rovers, conclusion; Three Penny Opera, undated (Box 237, Cassette 146)
    - Jewish, 1972-1979 (Box 15, Folder 7-8)
    - Jewish, 1971-1975 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - Jewish Commission, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Jewish Life, 1988-1989 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Jewish Question, 1983-1994 (Box 16, Folder 5-7)
    - Jose R: Lectures #64, 1975 March 22 (Box 235, Cassette 103)
    - Jose R: Class #65, 1975 March 22 (Box 235, Cassette 104)
    - Johnson, Oakley C., 1968 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Labor, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Labor, 1970 (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
    - Labor Commission, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Labor: Finance, 1971 (Box 220, Folder 3)
    - Labor: Jobs, 1971 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Labor and Task Force, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Labor and Task Force, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Latin America and Puerto Rico, 1967-1968 (Box 220, Folder 4)
    - Leadership, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 2-3)
    - Leadership: Cadre, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Leadership: Job Application, Cadre, 1981-1983 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Leadership: Political Bureau and Secretariat, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Leadership: Structures and Functioning, 1988 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Leadership: Structure and Leadership, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 8-9)
    - Leadership and Its Work, 1980-1981 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Leadership and Structure, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Lightfoot Book, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
    - Lincoln Brigade Materials, 1972 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Lennon Appeal, 1970-1975 (Box 19, Folder 4-5, Box 234, Cassette 222-223)
    - Lists, 1963, 1973 (Box 19, Folder 6-8)
    - Lists, 1973-1974 (Box 20, Folder 1-3)
    - Literature, 1971-1973 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Line of March (A Marxist-Leninist Journal of Rectification), 1984-1985 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Lumer, Hyman: Memorial, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Mann, Harry: Writings, 1989 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Manual on Organization, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 8-10)
    - Manual on Organization, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
    - Manual on Organization: Draft, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 3)